American Academy in Rome
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- New York Office, 1855-circa 1981, undated, Series 3:; (box 17-32; 15 linear ft.)
  - Records of Staff, 1919-1950, undated, 3.1:
    - Roscoe Guernsey (Executive Secretary) (Box 17, Reel 5777)
      - Carpenter, Rhys (Professor in Charge of Classical Studies), 1939-1945 (Box 18, Reel 5778)
        (includes correspondence concerning his appointment, passport problems, activities of fellows, publications)
      - Cash Prize in Architecture, 1941-1942 (Box 18, Reel 5778)
        (form letters about the competition, programs for preliminary and final competitions; see also Regional Competitions for 1941 and 1942)
      - Clark, Charles Upson (Professor of Classical Studies; Director, School of Classical Studies), undated, 1916-1919 (Box 18, Reel 5778)
        (includes correspondence about the library, travel plans, income tax, opinions of executive committee members regarding continuing Clark's appointment, news of Clark's activities after returning to the U.S.
      - Classical Senior Scholarships, A-Z, 1945 (Box 18, Reel 5778)
        (correspondence with competitors, letters from recipients outlining their plans for graduate studies)
      - Classical Society of the American Academy in Rome, undated, 1938-1948 (Box 18, Reel 5778-5779)
        (includes constitution of the Classical Society of the American Academy in Rome, form letters to former students, lists of contributors to the classical school fund, lists of committees, annual reports, correspondence with officers, "Directory of the School of Classical Studies," newsletters)
      - Collaborative Problem, 1920-1931 (Box 18, Reel 5779)
        (includes problem statements, jury reports, correspondence about regulations and funding, critiques of submissions)
      - College and University Annual Subscriptions, School of Classical Studies, 1920-1931 (Box 18, Reel 5779)
      - Committee on the School of Classical Studies, 1921-1945 (Box 18, Reel 5779)
        (includes correspondence concerning staffing, summer school, certificates and diplomas, news of students and staff, committee appointments,)
      - Council of the Academy, 1919-1944 (Box 18, Reel 5779)
        (includes lists of members, report, letters of appointment and acceptance)
      - Crane, Arthur H. (see Boring, William A.) (Box 18, Reel 5779)
      - Curtis, C. Densmore (Professor of Archaeology), 1919-1925 (Box 18, Reel 5779)
        (includes correspondence concerning publications)
      - Customs Duty, 1921-1942 (Box 18, Reel 5779)
        (correspondence and receipts regarding duty and other taxes paid on international shipments)
      - Davico, Riccardo (Secretary, Rome), 1927; 1935-1945 (Box 18, Reel 5779)
        (financial reports, correspondence mainly regarding financial matters, also about shipments of student work, news of staff activities, help from Swiss Legation during World War II; detailed accounts of condition of grounds, buildings and occupants, with lists of equipment and supplies needed, report of theft at Villa Bellacci, repairs completed)
      - Davico-Longobardi Salary and Dollar Balances, 1940-1945 (Box 18, Reel 5779)
      - de Daehn, Peter (Assistant Librarian; Acting Librarian), 1935-1945 (Box 18, Reel 5779)
        (includes accounts of portion of salary held in New York, also correspondence concerning publications, staffing and work responsibilities, salary supplement for de Daehn, inquiries from nephew requesting information about de Daehn's welfare)
      - Dinsmoor, William B. (Trustee; Acting Director, Rome, 1944 (Box 18, Reel 5779)
        (July 1944-April 1945, unable to secure passport to travel to Rome to assume duties; includes correspondence about use of academy facilities by the Office of War Information)
      - Donor Acknowledgments, undated, 1921-1937 (Box 18, Reel 5779)
      - Donor Lists, undated, 1920-1938 (Box 18, Reel 5779)
      - Ely Loan Fund, 1916-1945 (Box 19, Reel 5779)
        (includes applications, also correspondence concerning committee meetings, repayment of loans)
      - Endowment, undated, 1919-1941 (Box 19, Reel 5779)
        (includes lists of contributors, correspondence with and about donors, also concerning fundraising, Horatio Parker Memorial Fellowship)
      - Fairbanks, Frank P. (Professor in Charge, School of Fine Arts) (folders slightly out of order on microfilm), 1921-1930 (Box 19, Reel 5779-5780)
        (includes correspondence about student work, collaborative problems, exhibitions, competitions, shipments, request for self-portraits of former fellows, inventories of studio furnishings, death notice, brochure and letter announcing the opening of a girls' finishing school in Rome operated by Mrs. Fairbanks and her daughter)
      - Faulkner, Barry (Annual Professor, School of Fine Arts; Chairman, Committee on the School of Fine Arts), 1922-1946 (Box 19, Reel 5780)
        (includes cost estimate for Rome Prize in painting competition, correspondence concerning Ward-Thrasher Memorial, Faulkner's appointment as annual professor, fellows, competitions, nominations, suggestions for future development when the academy reopens following World War II, proposed program of study for fellows)
      - Fellows--Employment, 1922-1934 (Box 19, Reel 5780)
        (correspondence about helping fellows find academic positions)
      - Fellows Serving in U.S. Armed Forces, undated, 1942-1945 (Box 19, Reel 5780)
      - Fellows-Travel Arrangements, undated, 1922-1941 (Box 19, Reel 5780)
      - Fellowship in Architecture-Accredited Schools, 1930-1939 (Box 19, Reel 5780)
      - Fellowship in Architecture-Miscellaneous Applications, 1924-1930 (Box 19, Reel 5780)
      - Fellowship in Architecture-Recipients, 1919-1938 (Box 19, Reel 5780)
        (correspondence with and about architects Philip T. Shutze (1919), James Kellum Smith (1920), William Douglas (1924), Stuart M. Shaw (1925), Clarence D. Badgeley (1926), Homer D. Pfeiffer (1927), Cecil Clair Briggs (1928), B. Kenneth Johnston (1929), Walter L. Reichardt (1930), Henry D. Mirick (1931), Olindo Grossi (1933), Robert A. Weppner (1934), George T. Licht (1935), Richard Ayers (1936), Richard G. Hartshore (1937), and Erling F. Iverson (1938))
      - Fellowship in Classical Studies--Competition, 1929 and 1939 (Box 19, Reel 5780)
      - Fellowship in Classical Studies--Miscellaneous Applications, 1929-1939 (Box 19, Reel 5780)
      - Fellowship in Classical Studies--Recipients, 1913-1941 (Box 19, Reel 5780-5781)
        (Lists of fellows in classical studies, 1913-1926 and correspondence with and about Emily L. Wadsworth (1919); Walter R. Bryan and Ethel L. Chubb (1920); Homer F. Rebert and Robert S. Rogers (1923); Marion E. Blake, Florence H. Robinson, and Inez Scott (1924); Lillian B. Lawler and Charles A. Robinson, Jr. (1925); John Day, Frederick La Motte Santee, and Lillian Starr (1926); Henry Collice, Howard Comfort, and Mildred M. McConnell (1927); Raymond T. Ohl, James Oliver, and Irene Rosenszweig (1928); Franklin W. Jones, George E. McCracken, and Edmund T. Silk (1929); H. Ess Askew, Elizabeth C. Evans, and Adele Jeanne Kibre(1930); Alfred Gelstharp, Jr. and Agnes Kirsoff Lake (1931); Chester Carr Greene, Jr., Bernard M. Peebles, and Dorothy Schullian (1932); Aline L. Abaescherli, George K. Boyce, and Meyer Reinhold (1933); Richard A. Lattimore, Naphtali Lewis, and George J. Siefert, Jr. (1934); Susan M. Savage, Lucy T. Shoe, and Walter F. Snyder (1936); William T. Avery and Erling C. Olsen (1937); Frances G. Blank, Miriam Friedman, and Chester G. Starr, Jr. (1938); Donald Brown and Delight Tolles (1939); Lester C. Houck (1940); Robert A. Brooks, Robert A. Long, and Herbert Strange (1941))
      - Fellowship in Fine Arts--Competition, 1920-1923 (Box 20, Reel 5781)
      - Fellowship in Fine Arts--Miscellaneous Applications, 1922, 1925 (Box 20, Reel 5781)
      - Fellowship in Fine Arts--Recipients, 1919-1939 (Box 20, Reel 5781)
        (correspondence with and about Salvatore Lascari (1919); Cecere Gaetano and Carlo Ciampaglia (1920); Harry Poole Camden, Jr. and A. Clement Finley, Jr. (1924); Walker Hancock and Michael J. Mueller (1925); Deane Keller and Joseph Kiselewski (1926); George H. Snowden (1927); Donald M. Mattison and David K. Rubins (1928); John M. Sitton and Sidney B. Waugh (1929); Salvatore De Maio and William M. Simpson (1930); Harry G. Ackerman and Warren T. Mosman (1931); James O. Mahoney (1932); Robert Amendola and Daniel Boza (1933); Gilbert Baneuer and Reuben Kramer (1934); Robert B. Green and Gifford MacGregor Proctor (1935); William Boyhan and Theodore Harrison Gibbs (1936); John Amore and Clifford E. Jones (1937); Harry A. Davis, Jr. and George Koren (1938); J. Robert McCloskey and Robert L. Pippenger (1939))
      - Fellowship in Landscape Architecture--Competition, 1920-1938 (Box 20, Reel 5781)
      - Fellowship in Landscape Architecture--Miscellaneous Applications, 1934 (Box 20, Reel 5781)
      - Fellowship in Landscape Architecture--Recipients, 1915-1939 (Box 20, Reel 5781)
        (correspondence with and about Edward Lawson (1915 [completed after World War I]); Ralph Griswold (1920); Norman T. Newton (1923); Thomas D. Price (1925); Richard K. Webel (1926); Charles R. Sutton (1929); Richard C. Murdock and Neil H. Park (1931); Henry Chabanne and George Nelson (1932); Morris E. Trotter, Jr. (1933); Alden Hopkins (1934); James M. Lister (1935); Robert S. Kitchen (1936); John F. Kirkpatrick (1937); Stuart M. Mertz (1938); Frederick William Edmondson (1939))
      - Fellowship in Musical Composition--Competition, 1929, 1938 (Box 20, Reel 5781)
      - Fellowship in Musical Composition--Recipients, 1921-1939 (Box 20, Reel 5781-5782)
        (correspondence with and about Leo Sowerby (1921), George H. Elwell (1924); Robert Sanders (1925), Roger Sessions (1928); Normand Lockwood (1929), Werner Jansson (1930), Herbert R. Inch (1931), Vittorio Giannini (1932), Hunter Johnson (1933), Samuel Barber (1935), Kent W. Kennan (1936), Frederick Woltmann (1937), Charles Nagasaki (1938), and William Denny (1939))
      - Finance Committee, 1933-1949 (Box 20, Reel 5782)
      - Fraser, Leon (Treasurer), 1937-1945 (Box 20, Reel 5782)
        (includes biographical notes, census of property in foreign countries, and correspondence about McKim trust fund and estate)
      - French, Daniel Chester (Trustee; McKim Memorial Committee), 1919-1932 (Box 20, Reel 5782)
        (includes correspondence concerning shipment of Jennewein's work, possibility of maintaining studios in New York for use by returning fellows, resignation from board)
      - Garden Club of America Fellowship, 1926 (Box 20, Reel 5782)
        (correspondence regarding fellowship for landscape architecture)
      - G.I. Fellowships, 1945 (Box 20, Reel 5782)
        (correspondence about a proposal to offer fellowships to highly qualified soldiers who wish to study in Italy after discharge from the Army, notes on men interviewed for fellowships, finances)
      - Greene, Jerome D. (Trustee), 1937 (Box 20, Reel 5782)
        (letter from Ambassador Phillips conveying his positive regard for the academy)
      - Gugler, Eric (Trustee), 1918-1945 (Box 20, Reel 5782)
        (includes request for assistance with a Latin inscription, correspondence concerning a farewell gift for director Stevens, competitions)
      - Hammond, Mason (Professor in Charge of Classical Studies; Committee on the School of Classical Studies), 1935-1944 (Box 20, Reel 5782)
        (includes detailed administrative suggestions for the Classical School, suggestions regarding fellows and procedures for selecting fellows, dispersal of surplus academy publications, assisting former fellows in finding employment, detailed summary of war time conditions at the academy and information about remaining staff, Hammond's plans for military service, news of former students in military service, discussion of Hammond becoming acting director in Rome and factors influencing his ultimate decision not to accept the offer)
      - Hendrickson, G. L. (Professor in Charge, School of Classical Studies), undated, 1919-1921 (Box 20, Reel 5782)
        (includes correspondence concerning summer school)
      - Hewlett, James Monroe (Director, Rome), 1931-1939 (Box 20, Reel 5782)
        (includes correspondence about staff and fellows, finances, reducing expenses, collaborative problems, "Special Report on the Disappearance of Werner Janssen's Bound Volumes of Musical Compositions," exhibitions, text of Professor Lamond's speech on the occasion of Mussolini's visit to the academy, housing, closing of Atelier, shipment of student work, trustee opinions about continuing Hewlett's appointment, text of Hewlett's radio address about the work of the Academy, Siro Maronita College's plans for expansion next door to the academy)
      - Institute of International Education, Paris, France, 1934-1936 (Box 21, Reel 5782)
        (invitation to become an affiliate, academy's acceptance)
      - Inventory of Furniture and Equipment, 1941 (Box 21, Reel 5782)
      - James, Henry (First Vice President; Acting President), 1945 (Box 21, Reel 5782)
        (includes correspondence concerning leave courses for servicemen to be held at the academy, question of whether employees on academy payroll may also accept payment for war work)
      - Thomas Spencer Jerome Lectureship, 1917-1944 (Box 21, Reel 5782)
        (correspondence concerning committee business, Jerome estate's investments)
      - Johnson, Allan C. (Committee on the School of Classical Studies), 1944-1945 (Box 21, Reel 5782)
        (includes correspondence concerning retirement age for academy faculty, advisory council)
      - Juries, 1925-1940 (Box 21, Reel 5782)
        (letters of appointment and acceptance)
      - Kendall, William M. (Trustee), 1921, 1936 (Box 21, Reel 5782)
      - Kendall, William M.--Estate of, 1938-1942 (Box 21, Reel 5782)
        (includes copy of his will naming the academy a beneficiary, memorial to Kendall by Royal Cortissoz)
      - La Farge, C. Grant (Secretary), undated, 1915-1939 (Box 21, Reel 5782)
        (includes correspondence regarding resignation of Edwin H. Blashfield from the board, memorial minute for Ferruccio Vitale, memorial minute for C. Grant La Farge)
      - Lamond, Felix (Professor of Music), undated, 1920-1941 (Box 21, Reel 5782-5783)
        (correspondence about concerts, endowment committee, activities of fellows, Music magazine, Lamond's typical daily schedule, juries and competitions, problems with married students, text of radio address about the academy by Lamond, his music colony at Roquebrune, condolences on the death of Professor Lamond)
      - Lamond Fund [Lucretia Perry Osborn (Mrs. Henry Fairfield Osborn) Trust], 1926-1931 and 1940 (Box 21, Reel 5783)
        (trust agreement and correspondence concerning distribution of the fund after Lamond's death)
      - Landscape Architecture, 1919-1946 (Box 21, Reel 5783)
        (includes correspondence about extending fellowships, fundraising for fellowships, circular of American Society of Landscape Architects outlining minimum professional training, list of participants in all landscape architecture competitions, fellowship competitions and procedures, exhibitions, accredited schools, Garden Club of America fellowship, reports on activities of former fellows)
      - Lazarus Fellowship, 1917-1940 (Box 21, Reel 5783)
        (includes correspondence concerning the Metropolitan Museum's use of work by Lazarus Fellows, appointment of fellows, list of fellows, resolutions of Metropolitan Museum trustees, increase in stipends)
      - Leases, 1936-1943 (Box 21, Reel 5783)
        (regarding office space at 101 Park Ave., New York City)
      - Library Donations, 1923-1930 (Box 21, Reel 5783)
      - Library Orders, 1922-1945 (Box 21, Reel 5783)
      - Lord, Day & Lord (Legal Counsel), 1938-1944 (Box 21, Reel 5783)
        (includes correspondence regarding taxes, status of academy students under Selective Service Act)
      - Lord, Milton E. (Librarian), 1925-1930 (Box 21, Reel 5783)
        (mainly concerns his appointment)
      - McClellan, George B. (Trustee; Vice President; Chairman, Library Committee), undated, 1922-1938 (Box 21, Reel 5783)
        (includes correspondence about fellows, budget, library committee business, arrangements for McClellan's trip to Rome)
      - McCrea, Nelson G. (Professor of Classical Studies), 1921 (Box 21, Reel 5783)
        (includes letter describing Villa Bellacci where MacCrea might live McDaniel, Walton Brooks (Annual Professor of Classical Studies), 1921)
      - Mead, William R. (President), 1920-1927 (Box 21, Reel 5783)
        (fundraising and Endowment Fund, Polasek's bust of McKim, exhibitions, establishment of an Atelier, fellows, administrative matters, competitions)
      - Mellon, Edward P. (Trustee; Chairman, Committee on Endowment), 1919-1925 (Box 21, Reel 5783)
        (includes correspondence about fellows, endowment fund)
      - Mendell, Clarence W. (Committee on Publications), 1932-1941 (Box 21, Reel 5783)
      - Moe, Henry Allen (Trustee), 1943 (Box 21, Reel 5783)
      - Morey, Charles R. (Director, Rome), 1945 (Box 21, Reel 5783)
        (includes correspondence concerning salaries in Rome, leave courses at the academy for U.S. servicemen, condition of Villa Chiaraviglio
      - Morgan, J. Pierpont, Jr. (Trustee), 1920 (Box 21, Reel 5783)
        (board resolution electing J. P. Morgan, Jr. a Founder of the American Academy in Rome in gratitude for debt cancellation)
      - Music Department, 1920-1942 (Box 21, Reel 5783)
        (includes a brief history of the department, proxies approving establishment of the department, fundraising, correspondence concerning musical fellowships and competitions, activities of fellows, dismissal of fellow Winter Watts, Horatio Parker Fellowship)
      - Music Publications, 1937-1945 (Box 21, Reel 5783)
        (includes orders, correspondence regarding music manuscripts being considered for publication, contracts, invoices)
      - Nominating Committee, 1930-1944 (Box 21, Reel 5783)
        (mainly notifications and acceptances of election)
      - Norton, Charles D. (Trustee), 1919-1923 (Box 21, Reel 5783)
        (includes correspondence about beginning to acquire additional land on the Janiculum, Norton's resolution for establishing a permanent Department of Music)
      - Ogle, Marbury B. (Professor in Charge of Classical Studies), 1931-1934 (Box 21, Reel 5783)
        (includes correspondence regarding his appointment, fellows, annual trip to Greece, advisory council, finances)
      - Osborn, Mrs. Henry Fairfield (Donor), 1922-1928 (Box 21, Reel 5783)
        (includes correspondence concerning Gala Concert, fundraising for the Department of Music)
      - Parrish, Samuel L. (Donor), 1924-1929 (Box 21, Reel 5783)
        (includes correspondence concerning sculpture fellowships, Parrish's donation, appointment of Parrish Art Museum Fellow)
      - Pine, John B. (Legal Counsel), 1920-1922 (Box 21, Reel 5783)
        (correspondence about revision of by-laws and constitution, memorial resolution)
      - Platt, Charles (Committee on the School of Fine Arts; President), 1922-1933 (Box 21, Reel 5783-5784)
        (includes correspondence concerning executive committee business, fellows, staff duties, housing, publications, architectural competition procedures, suggestions for additions to work required of the architectural students, married students, collaborative problem, exhibitions, appointment of director Hewlett, establishment of Alumni Medal, shipment of student work, reducing expenses and salaries in Rome, discussion of closing Villa Aurelia, memorial resolution)
      - Pope, John Russell (President), 1935-1938 (Box 21, Reel 5784)
        (includes correspondence about the library, staffing, finances, memorial resolution)
      - Prix de Rome Medal (designed by Harry Camden), undated, 1940-1942 (Box 22, Reel 5784)
        (includes announcement of competition and related correspondence, arrangements for production of the winning design, thank you letters from recipients)
      - Publications, Annual Contributors Pamphlet, 1927-1928 (Box 22, Reel 5784)
        (correspondence concerning specifications and production)
      - Publications, Mailing Lists, 1928-1939 (Box 22, Reel 5784)
      - Publications, Memoirs of The American Academy in Rome and Monographs Published, 1920-1941 (Box 22, Reel 5784)
        (includes lists of orders, correspondence concerning production, expenses, copyright)
      - Publications, Orders, 1920-1947 (Box 22, Reel 5784)
      - Publications, Villas and Grounds of Italy by Amey Aldrich and John Walker, 1938-1941 (Box 22, Reel 5784)
        (distribution list, correspondence regarding marketing of the pamphlet, orders)
      - Publicity, undated, 1921-1944 (Box 22, Reel 5784)
        (news releases and related correspondence, invoices for printing)
      - Rand, Edward K. (Trustee; Committee on the School of Classical Studies; Committee on Publications), 1919-1931 (Box 22, Reel 5784)
        (includes correspondence concerning committee on publications business, summer school, contributing colleges)
      - Regional Competitions, 1941 and 1942 (Box 22, Reel 5784-5785)
        (includes announcement of competition for cash awards when war time conditions made it impossible to send fellows to Rome, correspondence with members of the Committee on the School of Fine Arts, participating institutions; lists of districts and supervisors, budgets, schedules, reorganization of districts, lists of jurors; see also: Cash Prize in Architecture)
      - Rolfe, John C. (Professor of Classics; Committee on the School of Classical Studies), 1920-1940 (Box 22, Reel 5785)
        (includes correspondence concerning taxes, juries, publications, method of selecting fellows)
      - School of Classical Studies, undated, 1938-1943 (Box 22, Reel 5785)
        (includes form letters addressed to the Friends of the School of Classical Studies, mainly concerning fundraising; also, letters about the Classical Society, scholarship competition, placement)
      - School of Classical Studies, Advisory Council, 1922-1945 (Box 22, Reel 5785)
        (includes correspondence about representatives appointed to the advisory council, contributing colleges, juries, fundraising, prize scholarships; also, lists of members, committees, juries)
      - School of Classical Studies, College and University Annual Subscriptions, 1920-1931 (Box 22, Reel 5785)
      - School of Classical Studies, Lists of Directors and Professors, 1895-1933 (Box 22, Reel 5785)
      - School of Classical Studies, Lists of Students/Fellows, 1895-1933 (Box 22, Reel 5785)
      - School of Classical Studies, Summer Sessions, 1923-1939 (Box 23, Reel 5785-5786)
        (no sessions held 1933-1936; includes correspondence concerning publicity, appointment of Grant Showerman as director of the program, enrollment, form letters to participants, memorial book fund, discontinuation of summer sessions due to the Depression, requests to reinstate the program, plans for resuming the program, hiring of Professor Rowell, curriculum, travel arrangements, pension reservations; sample diploma, report)
      - School of Fine Arts--Advisory Council, 1924-1928 (Box 23, Reel 5786)
        (includes form letter outlining council functions, letters from colleges supporting the idea of establishing a council with recommendations for representatives, letters of appointment and acceptance, fellowship competitions; also, list of members and jury chairmen)
      - Shipments of Students' Work, undated, 1932-1938 (Box 23, Reel 5786)
      - Smith, James Kellum (Committee on the School of Fine Arts; Acting Treasurer; President), 1935-1945 (Box 23, Reel 5786)